Emily Ostrow

Blue bell, PA • linkedin.com/in/emily-ostrow-81796396 • emilyostrow.com

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

5+ years of experience working on research projects in evolutionary biology, with a focus in infectious diseases, parasitology, and genomics using computational biology. Experiences in project coordination of projects focusing on molecular genetics. Wrote grant proposals and raised over \$150,000 in a fellowship and grants. Published first author peer-reviewed articles, presented at national conferences.

WORK EXPERIENCE

University Of Kansas · Lawrence, KS

Graduate Research Fellow • Aug 2018 - Aug 2023

- Wrote effective grant proposals and communicated with stakeholders as demonstrated by raising over \$150,000 to fully fund my PhD research
- Creative research development skills, resulting in novel host and parasite transmission genomic research using machine learning techniques and landscape genomics
- Coordinated research studies and experiments in appropriate timelines using bioinformatics data analysis techniques and contributing to open science by publishing original code on GitHub
- Excellent project management and supervision, managing multiple projects and ~7 students to generate genomic data using hundreds of lab samples for laboratory projects
- Wrote and published technical reports in journals, resulting in multiple first author peer reviewed articles and national presentations
- Developed materials for and led public outreach events at the natural history museum and local parks in coordination with community partners

Graduate Teaching Assistant • Aug 2018 - May 2019

- Excellent oral and written communication skills, evidenced by presenting complex biological concepts to diverse audiences
- Experienced managing large groups, having taught two courses including introductory biology and evolution
- · Developed teaching materials and evaluated learning outcomes for evolution discussion groups

Academy Of Natural Sciences Of Drexel University · Philadelphia, PA

Student Research Associate • Sep 2014 - Jun 2018

- Lead field research for three years and managed the data collection of 15+ students and volunteers, resulting in over 2,000 biological samples collected for disease surveillance related to epidemiology and public health
- Contributed to database and data management of biological disease samples and their metadata, which included disease tracking, quality assurance, and reporting
- Collaboration with external partners to gain financial support and access to biological samples
- · Designed assays for disease detection using PCR and qPCR
- Developed and maintained a blood film repository including thousands of disease voucher samples from multiple researchers

Girl Scouts of NE Kansas and NW Missouri · Overland Park · Board

STEM Advisory Council • May 2020 - May 2022

- Served and volunteered as a subject matter expert for Girl Scout STEM education strategic planning
- Advised on 5 year strategic plan development for the creation of a regional science center for excellence
- Acted as a liaison between University of Kansas outreach groups and the regional Girl Scouts STEM council

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

University Of Kansas • Lawrence, KS, USA • GPA: 3.84 • Aug 2018 - Aug 2023

Masters of Science in Environmental Science

Drexel University • Philadelphia, PA • GPA: 3.88 • Sep 2013 - Jun 2018

Bachelors of Science in Environmental Science

Drexel University • Philadelphia, PA • GPA: 3.88 • Sep 2013 - Jun 2018

AWARDS & SCHOLARSHIPS

Graduate Research Fellowship Program

National Science Foundation

Ficken Research Award

American Ornithological Society

Ornithology Department Grant

University of Kansas

Entomology Endowment Grant

University of Kansas

SKILLS

Data Visualization, DNA Extraction, Funding Acquisition, Genomic Library Preparation, Genomics/Genetics, GitHub, Graphic Design, High Performance Computing, Mentoring, Next Generation Sequencing, PCR/qPCR, Project Management, R Programming Language, Science Communication, Team Leadership, Unix/Linux Command Line